Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
So let's see, today's דף daf is ג. Gimmel. We pick up
on ב עמוד ב. Bet amud Bet. Where are we? Remind tell
me. Doba sent me the information.
I've got it at about 12, 15 lines from the bottom. The
beginning of the line is
אמר
רבא.
Amar
Rava.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, thank you.
And the end is... great, okay.
So ב עמוד ב, Bet amud Bet, אמר רבא Amar Rava about
12-14 lines from the bottom, thank you. And
so let me just say a few brief words about the מסכת
masechet because I didn't have a chance to introduce this yesterday.
Later on in the מסכת masechet there'll be things not related to
מגילה, Megilla, a lot of interesting things about בית כנסת beit knesset
and about תפילה tefilla and קריאת התורה, kriat hatorah, but in terms
of the מגילה Megilla issues, you know one of the things I
just want to point out right at the beginning that's a really
important theme that we're going to see today but that I think
is central to this מסכת, masechet, which also relates to חנוכה Chanukah
but חנוכה Chanukah doesn't have a מסכת masechet devoted to it, you
know, is the authority of instituting a rabbinic holiday. Where does that
come from creating a new holiday in the calendar?
And that's something that gets subtly or not so subtly addressed in
this מסכת masechet together with the fact of the adding of a
ספר sefer to תנ"ך, Tanakh, particularly a ספר sefer that doesn't even
mention God's name, depending on when you think that אסתר Esther was
written. Was it written after the בניין הבית השני binyan habayit hasheni
began or before? It might have been the last ספר sefer because
חגי זכריה מלאכי Chaggai Zecharia Malachi were right at the beginning or
you know end of the גלות galut beginning of the בית שני.
bayit sheni. But even if it wasn't the last ספר sefer it
was next to the last ספר, sefer, one of the next to
the last ספרים, sfarim, and doesn't even have God's name, and you
know then it becomes one of the ספרי תנ"ך. sifrei Tanakh. And
you know that's alluded to in the מדרש midrash where אסתר Esther
says אסתר Esther says to the חכמים, Chachamim, כתבוני לדורות. Kitvuni l'dorot.
You know, write me for generations. And the גמרא Gemara has a
discussion about whether
אסתר Esther was ניתנה להיכתב nitna lehikatev or not, whether it was
given to be written or not, which might mean we'll discuss whether
it was included in the ספרי תנ"ך. sifrei Tanakh. So you have
these sort of interesting and all the attempt to try to justify
אסתר מן התורה מנין מרדכי מן התורה מנין. Esther min hatorah minayin
Mordechai min hatorah minayin. So you have these whole major questions about
the adding of אסתר Esther to the ספרי תנ"ך sifrei Tanakh and
the adding of a new holiday. And in that one line that
I just mentioned to you where אסתר Esther says כתבוני לדורות Kitvuni
l'dorot to the rabbis, it's also sort of the question about indicating
that the ultimate authority rests in the hands of the rabbis. Like
the rabbis are going to decide whether אסתר Esther is one of
the ספרי תנ"ך. sifrei Tanakh. Why do we keep the מגילה? Megilla?
Why do we keep פורים? Purim? You already got in the very
first עמוד amud of the גמרא Gemara an interesting
multi-vocal response to this where the גמרא Gemara says you know where
does this come from that you have all these different days? And
the גמרא Gemara says like this, the גמרא Gemara says let's take
a look.
כולהו אנשי כנסת הגדולה תקנינוהו. kulu Anshei Knesset HaGedola Tikninuhu.
All of this was established by the אנשי כנסת הגדולה. Anshei Knesset
HaGedola. Where was it hinted to in the פסוק? pasuk? And then
we show where it was hinted to in the פסוק. pasuk. So
are we keeping פורים Purim because of the authority of the מגילה
Megilla and because it's in the פסוקים psukim or are we keeping
it because ultimately the rabbis look at the פסוקים psukim and the
אנשי כנסת הגדולה, Anshei Knesset HaGedola, it was hinted in the פסוקים
psukim but the אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei Knesset HaGedola ultimately it's rabbinic
authority which determines why we are keeping the מגילה. Megilla. So those
I think are some of the really central themes that are going
on here. Where is the authority of this being one of the
ספרי תנ"ך? sifrei Tanakh? Where is the authority of us keeping פורים?
Purim? How much is that because of this as a ספר תנ"ך
sefer Tanakh and how much is that because of ultimately אנשי כנסת
הגדולה, Anshei Knesset HaGedola, the רבנן, Rabbanan, כתבוני לדורות, Kitvuni l'dorot, that
it's the rabbis ultimately who are the arbitrators of why this becomes
a ספר תנ"ך, sefer Tanakh, why this becomes a holiday. So right
already in the beginning you had some of that and that's really
a theme that's going to continue today and going to continue for
a good part of the מסכת, masechet, something to really look out
for. I'll say one other interesting thing about this, about the סוגיה
sugya we're in the middle of which is the idea of י"א
י"ב י"ג י"ד. Yud-Alef Yud-Bet Yud-Gimmel Yud-Daled. You know it seems very
very bizarre that this idea that you can have multiple days to
do a holiday. And you're not really doing the holiday, you're doing
the מצות מגילה, mitzvat Megilla, but still the option of multiple days.
But we should note that that's just expanding on something that's bizarre
to begin with which is a holiday that's celebrated at two separate
times. Right? And we're not just talking about a second day of
יום טוב yomtov for יום טוב שני, yomtov sheni, you know, we're
talking about fundamentally
some people celebrate it on the 14th and some people celebrate it
on the 15th. And this idea is where else do you ever
have this? One of the whole ideas of a central calendar right
is it unifies everybody in the observance of the holidays and that's
certainly what creates a whole sense of your religious community that you
observe the holidays on the same time.
itself we should note
how unique how truly unique that is and therefore the idea that
then well once we're given some זמנים zmanim then זמנים הרבה תיקנו
להם חכמים zmanim harbei tiknu lahem chachamim then we can sort of
even have a little bit more latitude okay it seems you know
but it's a little excessive but that just I think highlights the
fact that already the fact that there are two different days for
different cities is never you know nowhere else in the sort of
in the in the liturgical calendar in the religious calendar. Yes.
Did the idea of local holidays predate this or postdate this?
Oh you mean like a פורים קטן Purim Katan or whatever?
Yeah there's like a local holiday for a city a holiday for
family.
Yeah that's true but that's but that's not like national you know
that's very private or local right a city right it's true it's
true. Yeah so it might be a little bit of yeah so
you have elements of that but that has the very nature of
local holidays. Yes.
Regarding the last thing written it looks from the פשט pshat although
it can't really be proven right that ספר עזרא נחמיה Sefer Ezra
Nechemia describes the last events that are described in תנ״ך. Tanakh.
Yes well that's a whole question. The גמרא Gemara basically assumes that
אסתר Esther was written between בית ראשון Bayit Rishon and בית שני
Bayit Sheni
scholars and רמב״ן Ramban disagree they say it was written in the
beginning of the בנין בית שני Binyan Bayit Sheni so that we'll
get to that but the גמרא'ס Gemara's general rule assumes it was
written before the events of עזרא ונחמיה. Ezra veNechemia. That is true
that is true. Okay so so let's continue here and see and
see where we are.
Can we take a question from yesterday?
I'd rather not because of limited time. I know דוב Dov told
me you have a question but I don't want to deal with
that one right now. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this
and the last thing we left off was the question about whether
you go from ימות יהושע בן נון Yemot Yehoshua bin Nun which
seems bizarre and I'll say something about that or whether you go
from מוקף חומה Mukaf Chomah from ימי אחשוורוש. Yemei Achashverosh.
So let's take a look.
I should say one thing about the issue of פרזים prazim as
opposed to כרך. kerach. You know the גמרא Gemara here based on
the פסוקים psukim in במדבר Bamidbar לבד מערי הפרזי הרבה מאד levad
me'arei haprazi harbei me'od you know ערי מוקפות arei mukkofot מוקף חומה
דלתים ובריח mukaf chomah dlatayim uvariach לבד מערי הפרזי הרבה מאד levad
me'arei haprazi harbei me'od that פסוק pasuk is from דברים Devarim assumes
you know פרזי prazi is unwalled and and as opposed to כרך
kerach as opposed to what it designates as כרכים krakhim which are
walled cities. I think the JPS translation you could check it it's
right there has when it says על כן היהודים הפרזים היושבים בערי
הפרזות al ken haYehudim haprazim hayoshvim be'arei haprazot says the Jews in
the in the
something like in the you know in the outlying towns that you
know and a פרזי prazi is in contrast to שושן הבירה Shushan
haBirah the non-capital city. So therefore if you read the פסוק pasuk
that way all it's saying is like anybody not in שושן Shushan
keeps the fourteenth day. שושן Shushan maybe keeps and the גמרא Gemara
seems to have a strange הוה אמינא hava amina maybe the fourteenth
and the fifteenth but the fourteenth and the fifteenth isn't such a
strange הוה אמינא hava amina because שושן Shushan right you know they
well okay the first major victory that they could have celebrated was
the fourteenth you know but then they continued fighting on the fourteenth
but at least the fourteenth you know had was also significant even
for שושן Shushan but even if it's only the fifteenth right it's
possible that a פשט pshat reading of the פסוקים psukim is that
everywhere else does the fourteenth and שושן Shushan maybe does the fifteenth
although again as you saw yesterday the מגילה Megillah never mentions what
are the non-פרזים prazim do. It says the פרזים prazim do on
the fourteenth and it talks about the fourteenth and the fifteenth and
that's that whole ambiguity that the גמרא Gemara tries to figure out
because it never explicitly says what the non-פרזים prazim do. But nevertheless
it's possible that a פשט pshat reading of the פסוקים psukim is
non-שושן Shushan versus שושן Shushan but the גמרא Gemara reads it walled
versus non-walled. One approach is אחשוורוש Achashverosh which at least somehow makes
sense sort of similar to שושן Shushan and this other approach of
יהושע בן נון Yehoshua bin Nun which doesn't seem to make any
sense which I'll say something about in a little bit but let's
start reading the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אלא שושן Ela Shushan I'll start one line before that דעבדי
כמאן de'avdi keman לא פרזים ולא מוקפין lo prazim velo mukafin if
you go from the time of יהושע בן נון Yehoshua bin Nun
what's שושן Shushan doing like? It's not right it's it's doing the
fifteenth but it's not the הלכה halakha the fifteenth it should follow
the fourteenth because the גמרא Gemara assumes that it was not מוקף
mukaf מימות יהושע בן נון. miyemot Yehoshua bin Nun. How the גמרא
Gemara knows that I don't know but maybe unless you know otherwise
that's what you have to assume. אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא
Rava ואיתימא כדי ve'iteima kadi and some say כדי kadi which might
mean nobody meaning anonymously
or it could be the name of a of a sage. שאני
שושן הואיל ונעשה בה נס. Shani Shushan ho'il vena'aseh bah nes. No
since the whole miracle is in שושן Shushan you know that's sort
of like the paradigm that becomes
that is the fifteenth even though everything else that sort of based
on it and the rule that we've developed actually שושן Shushan falls
outside of the rule. Okay now again it's so strange why that
rule but let's read a little bit more and then I'll get
back to that.
בשלמא לתנא דידן היינו דכתיב מדינה ומדינה ועיר ועיר. Bishlama letanna didan
hainu dikhtiv medinah umedinah ve'ir va'ir. So if you... So it sounds
like even within a מדינה medinah which presumably means like a walled
city there are distinctions and between עיר ir there are distinctions. So
let's take a look. מדינה ומדינה לחלק בין מוקפין חומה מימות יהושע
בן נון למוקף חומה מימות אחשורוש. medinah u'medinah l'chaleik bein mukafin chomah
miyemos Yehoshua bin Nun l'mukaf chomah miyemos Achashveirosh.
So מדינה ומדינה medinah u'medinah tells you that there are walled cities
and walled cities. Some that read on the 15th, some that read
on the 14th, depends when your wall was. Does it go back
to the time of יהושע בן נון Yehoshua bin Nun or only
from the time of אחשורוש? Achashveirosh? And according to our משנה mishnah
it would only go from the time of יהושע... Yehoshua... only those
walled cities. עיר ועיר ir v'ir and an עיר ir which is
not a walled city. So not all עיר ir are the same.
Why are not all עיר ir the same once we've already introduced
the distinction of ימות יהושע בן נון? yemos Yehoshua bin Nun? There's
another distinction to be made. נמי לחלק בין שושן לשאר עיירות nami
l'chaleik bein Shushan l'sh'ar ayarot because some things even that fall into
the עיר ir category i.e. שושן Shushan don't have the הלכה halachah
of an עיר. ir. Even though שושן Shushan is not walled from
the time of יהושע בן נון Yehoshua bin Nun it still reads
on the 15th, it's an exception, as opposed to the others which
read on the 14th. So that works. There are two distinctions that
need to be made: the rule of יהושע בן נון Yehoshua bin
Nun and not, and then שושן Shushan as the exception. אלא לרבי
יהושע בן קרחה. ella l'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. רבי יהושע בן קרחה
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha that says you go from the time of
אחשורוש. Achashveirosh. בשלמא מדינה ומדינה לחלק בין שושן לשאר עיירות. bishlama medinah
u'medinah l'chaleik bein Shushan l'sh'ar ayarot. So you need מדינה ומדינה medinah
u'medinah to tell you the basic rule of walled cities from the
time of אחשורוש. Achashveirosh. But then there's no other exceptions to be
made. That's the whole rule. אלא עיר ועיר למה לי? ella ir
v'ir lamah li? Why do you need to distinguish עיר ועיר? ir
v'ir? You've got your whole rule. אמר לך רבי יהושע בן קרחה.
amar lach Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Korcha would say back, ולתנא דידן מי ניחא? u'letanna didan mi
nicha? According to our תנא tanna does it really go? כיון דאית
ליה פרזי פרזי. keivan d'is lei prazi prazi. Once he already learns
out from the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah that we said yesterday from
the פסוקים psukim in דברים Devarim that you go from ימות יהושע
בן נון yemos Yehoshua bin Nun from unwalled, מדינה ומדינה למה לי?
medinah u'medinah lamah li? You already knew the rule from פרזי פרזי.
prazi prazi. So why do you need
מדינה ומדינה? medinah u'medinah? אלא דרשה הוא דאתא. ella drasha hu d'ata.
It's coming for a דרשה. drasha. וכדרבי יהושע בן לוי הוא דאתא
דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי. u'ched'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi hu d'ata d'amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. כרך וכל הסמוך לו. krach v'chol hasamuch lo.
מדינה ומדינה medinah u'medinah means there's a מדינה medinah and then there's
extensions of the מדינה. medinah. וכל הנראה עמו v'chol hanireh imo and
וכל הסמוך לו v'chol hasamuch lo counts as the כרך krach and
reads on the 15th. וכל הנראה עמו v'chol hanireh imo and whether
it's physically geographically nearby or maybe it's geographically distant but it's
visible, נידון ככרך nidon k'krach has the law of the כרך krach
and reads on the 15th. עד כמה? ad kamah? Now how distant
can it be that it's still considered part of the כרך? krach?
So now this is going to give you a sense of how
their scale is so totally different than ours. אמר רבי ירמיה ואיתימא
רבי חייא בר אבא. amar Rabbi Yirmiyah v'iseima Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba.
כמיחמתן לטבריא מיל. k'meichamtan l'Tveryah mil. Like the distance from חמתן Chamtan
to טבריה Tveryah which is a מיל. mil. A מיל mil is
a kilometer. Okay, that's how far away it could be, a whole
kilometer away and still be considered part of the city. ולימא מיל?
v'leima mil? Let them say a מיל. mil. אשמעינן דשיעורא דמיל כמה
הוי כמיחמתן לטבריה. ashmeinan d'shiura d'mil kamah havi k'meichamtan l'Tveryah. No, he
wants to tell you, give you the measurement that maybe you don't
know exactly how far a מיל mil is. Also maybe to give
you that as a nice graphic example that you have these two,
a village near a city and it's considered part of the city.
Now, a kilometer is very small. But you also have the principle
of נראה. nireh. סמוך samuch is even if it's not visible. The
גמרא Gemara will discuss how that can be. But then you have
נראה. nireh. If it's visible from the city even if it's not
סמוך samuch it also is part of the city and that's significant.
This is also very significant for nowadays reading in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. How
much when you continue to fill up from the original
walled city is it considered to be the extension of the city?
Does it have to be נראה? nireh? There are places obviously in
ירושלים Yerushalayim you can't see the old city and it's more than
a מיל mil away, but it's all continuously built up, right? So
these become very relevant discussions. I want to just say another point
though about this issue about the authority
of keeping פורים Purim and so on. You notice that what the
גמרא Gemara does almost naturally is that it uses the פסוקים psukim
in מגילה Megillah to do the normal type of דרשות drashot that
it does in the full way it would with a פסוק pasuk
from the
תורה. Torah. מדינה ומדינה ועיר ועיר, medinah u'medinah v'ir v'ir, every single
word has to mean something. So if it doesn't mean this then
this proves my point because obviously this extra word will tell you
this הלכה. halachah. But no wait, it's telling you a different הלכה
halachah if you don't need it for that הלכה. halachah. Exactly the
way it would do with a biblical פסוק. pasuk. Imagine the גמרא
Gemara doing this with any other ספר sefer in תנ"ך Tanakh other
than the מגילה. Megillah. The whole problem is how can we learn
anything from תנ"ך? Tanakh? Even if you make some type of a
גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah and you want to sort of
illuminate a biblical הלכה, halachah, there's always this question but how can
we learn it from תנ"ך? Tanakh? You're not allowed to learn anything
from תנ"ך. Tanakh. Here, right, everything is learned from these דרשות drashot
and we like do a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah from the מגילה
Megillah to אסתר. Esther. I mean a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah is
supposed to go back
to הר סיני. Har Sinai. Well how does it go back to
הר סיני Har Sinai if אסתר Esther was written like whatever it
was, 1500 years... I didn't have to do the math, but anyway,
a good millennium later. They are more afterwards, right? So it's being
treated really with the same way you would treat a biblical verse.
Obviously it makes sense because it's learning that to tell you the
weight of the מצוה mitzvah in the מגילה. Megillah. It's not telling
you just the weight of a מצוה mitzvah in the תורה, Torah,
right? So we're learning these דרשות drashot and from these דרשות drashot
we learn the מצוות mitzvot of the מגילה, Megillah, not מצוות mitzvot
of the תורה. Torah. But nevertheless, you know, the way it sort
of almost naturally makes this the same type of a weight as
the biblical verses, makes גזרה שוה gezerah shavah with the biblical verses,
has the same approach, really is showing, you know, sort of almost
through this rabbinic lens, through the rabbinic mode of דרשה drashah and
these types of hermeneutics, right, and תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-ba'al peh,
you know, giving it all this type of הלכה halakhic weight and
making this really implicitly, you know, incorporated into the ספרי תנ״ך Sifrei
Tanakh in ways even weightier than other of the ספרי תנ״ך Sifrei
Tanakh are. So again going back to that larger theme that I
raised at the beginning.
Yes, so it seemed to focus the observation a little bit because
it's not just the fact that you're talking about a מצוה דרבנן,
mitzvah d'rabbanan, right, the way that they did it was in the
same way, the model that they used was the way the תורה
Torah does things, but the strange thing is that any other דרבנן
d'rabbanan you just say this is the rule.
Exactly, right, so I agree, meaning the way you're allowed to do
this because you're learning not a מצוה mitzvah of the תורה Torah
but a מצוה mitzvah of the מגילה, Megillah, but you you are
ultimately anchoring it in the authority of the verses and that is
so you're you're doing the same mode. And also we should note
the sort of, you know, the bizarre nature of a גזרה שוה
gezerah shavah from here to a פסוק pasuk in the תורה, Torah,
right, so if you really mean a literal גזרה שוה gezerah shavah
as opposed to that the פסוק pasuk just reveals to us something.
But the גמרא Gemara seems to treat it as a גזרה שוה,
gezerah shavah, yes.
In determining whether a city had a wall in the time of
יהושע בן נון, Yehoshua bin Nun, how do we determine that because
archaeology has discovered—all
right, so I won't go into that, let's hold off on that
question. Okay, okay, so there you have that answer. Okay, so and
that obviously is a, as I said, running throughout this is דרש
darshaning the פסוקים psukim of the מגילה. Megillah. Okay, so now and
אמר רבי ירמיה ואיתימא רבי חייא בר אבא. amar Rabbi Yirmiyah v'itayma
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba. Now רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah and some say
רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba said the following. Now
ostensibly the only reason we're bringing this in is because it's the
same מאן דאמר, man d'amar, right, because we had רבי ירמיה Rabbi
Yirmiyah and some say in the name of רבי חייא בר אבא
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba כמה מחמצתא לטבריה מיל. kama machmatza l'Tveryah mil.
He was telling us the distance of a מיל mil in terms
of a nearby a village near a city. Let's take a look
though at this especially now that I sort of hyped you your
awareness to this theme that's going on here. So also says רבי
ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah and some say רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba the following:
מנצפ״ך צופים אמרום. mantzpach tzofim amrum. So מנצפ״ך mantzpach are the letters
מם נון צדי פא וכף mem nun tzadi pei and kaf that
have a different letter סופית sofit than when they're in the middle
of the word. Okay and he is saying that that idea, the
way to write those letters different in the middle of the word
and the end of the word, was said by the נביאים. nevi'im.
צופים אמרום tzofim amrum obviously it's a play on the word מנצפ״ך
mantzpach has צופים tzofim in it, you see the word צדי פא
ומם, tzadi pei and mem, מנצפ״ך צופים אמרום, mantzpach tzofim amrum, but
it means the נביאים nevi'im said it. Okay we the earlier we
didn't have the idea of a different letters in the middle and
the end, this came, this was taught us by the נביאים. nevi'im.
So the גמרא Gemara says ותסברא, v'tisbra, does that make sense that
the נביאים nevi'im innovated this? דהכתיב d'ha ktiv the verse says אלה
המצוות, eleh hamitzvot, these are the מצוות mitzvot that God commanded, right,
הר סיני, Har Sinai, שאין נביא רשאי לחדש דבר מעתה. she'ein navi
rashai l'chadesh davar mei'atah.
A prophet can't innovate some type of a מצוה mitzvah after the
תורה Torah has been given, so how can they innovate a new
way of writing the letters? Now of course the answer is like,
okay, that's not a מצוה, mitzvah, I mean you know, it's a
way of writing letters. Why you know, let's get some, you know,
let's get some perspective here. Now you could say it affects let's
say the כשרות kashrut of a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, right, you
know, if you maybe if you you know maybe if you say
that if it's not written, if the סופית sofit and the middle
way of writing are reversed, maybe the ספר תורה Sefer Torah would
be פסול, pasul, so it impacts a מצוה mitzvah in the תורה.
Torah. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't even spell that out, you know,
just says you're not allowed to innovate, שאין נביא רשאי לחדש
דבר מעתה. ein navi rashai l'chadesh davar mei'atah. ועוד v'od and in
addition אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, רב חסדא Rav Chisda says
מם וסמך שבלוחות בנס היו עומדים. mem v'samach she-baluchot b'nes hayu omdim.
The מם mem and סמך samach in the לוחות luchot were you
know, if the לוחות luchot were carved all the way through, so
the מם mem and סמך samach existed through a miracle. How is
that? Because if you have the מם סופית mem sofit and the
סמך, samach, what's holding that middle section, the hole of, you know,
suspended? It has to be a miracle. So obviously you see that
these letters existed at the the idea of the סופית sofit letters
existed at the time of the giving of the לוחות. luchot. Now
of course רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot say, well, maybe what the
נביאים nevi'im innovated was a different way of writing them in the
middle, maybe they were always the סופית sofit version. But okay, anyway,
that's the גמרא's Gemara question. So obviously it wasn't innovated. So the
גמרא Gemara says אין הכי הוה, in hachi hava, fine, they were
always there, ולא הוו ידעי הי באמצע תיבה והי בסוף תיבה. v'lo
hava yada'ei hai b'emtza teiva v'hai b'sof teiva.
That they didn't know or maybe one could say they weren't, you
know, they sort of weren't exact about which one would occur in
the middle of a word and which one. They would use both.
ואתו צופים ותקנו פתוחין באמצע תיבה וסתומין בסוף תיבה, ve'asu Tzofim vetiknu
psuchin b'emtza teiva v'stumin b'sof teiva,
and came along the נביאים Nevi'im and they established no we're gonna
be systematic about it. The open version of the letters in the
middle, and the closed version of the letters at the end. Now,
I meant to check this last night, I did not get a
chance, but I believe that in sort of,
you know, inscriptions, ancient inscriptions, you do find imprecision about that, that
sometimes you have a סופי sofi version occurring in the middle of
a word. That's correct, right? Do you ever have an open version
occurring at the end? You do sometimes, because I know a lot
of the things have a כ kaf at the end that's not
a כ סופי. kaf sofi. Right.
So the different end versions seem to have developed a little later.
Right. So, but they had... oh did they not? But we don't
have ancient inscriptions with the end versions of letters?
Well, the most ancient inscriptions are in the Canaanite, what we call
the Canaanite script. Okay. The אשור, Ashur, we don't have anything before
about the 22nd century BP.
Okay. So, anyway, so a lot of this actually does reflect the
development of the סופי sofi letters and whether they דווקא davka occur
at the end of the word. I think sometimes a מ סופי
mem sofi occurs in the middle of a word, I'm pretty sure.
Yeah, things like that, the...
if you follow this, it's in the למרבה
המשרה. l'marbe hamisrah.
Oh, right, right, right, right, right, that's maybe where I'm remembering it
from. Okay, so all of this does reflect a, you know, actual,
reasonable interpretation of history. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't like it though.
The גמרא Gemara says
סוף סוף, sof sof, nevertheless, at the end of the
day, אלה המצות שאין נביא רשאי לחדש דבר מעתה. eleh hamitzvos she'ein
navi rashai l'chadesh davar me'atah. A נביא navi cannot innovate. And a
נביא navi can't innovate. So even just to establish systematically what's in
the middle and what's at the end is not allowed? How could
that be? אלא שכחום וחזרו ויסדום. ella sheshachachum v'chazru v'yasdum. Fine, must
be we always had it in a particular way, the middle the
middle, the end the end. There was a period that it was
forgotten, and the נביאים Nevi'im just reminded us of the way it
always was. But ultimately they're not innovating, they're just teaching us, reminding
us of the way things always were. So now I want to
say two points. One should be pretty obvious, but the first point
I'll just make is that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has no problem with
this. Not only has no problem with this, as Charlie already told
us anyway, the current script that we have is not the script
that originally the ספר תורה Sefer Torah or things would have been
written in. This was a script that was taken from Assyria and
is not ancient Hebrew script, which is different. And actually the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi says not מ"ם וסמ"ך שבלוחות בנס היו עומדים, mem v'samech shebaluchos
b'nes hayu omdim, but ע' שבלוחות בנס היו עומדים. ayin shebaluchos b'nes
hayu omdim. Because in the ancient Hebrew script, the עין, ayin, like
the O, is the circle. So actually it was the עין ayin
that stood בנס, b'nes, because the עין ayin was the one that
was circular and was with a נס. nes. So not only do
they not have a problem with the question about which is in
the middle and which is at the end, but even a completely
different script, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has no problem assuming that fact changed.
Of course now the irony here should be obvious, right? We just
got through all of this thing about the מצוה של מגילה, mitzvah
shel Megillah, which is a complete חידוש chidush of דברי קבלה divrei
kabbalah and, you know, introducing all these פסוקים psukim which ultimately, you
know, get interpreted, whatever, and all this stuff comes quite late in
the period of the נביאים. Nevi'im. And here we refuse to say
that even the נביאים, Nevi'im, which could be the early נביאים, Nevi'im,
we refuse to say that they even innovated the question of exactly
the order, you know, which letters appear, the writing of the script,
even if it didn't even seem obviously that it was related to
a מצוה. mitzvah. As I said, you can make it related to
מצות כתיבת ספר תורה, mitzvos kesivas Sefer Torah, but the גמרא Gemara
doesn't even need that. Yeah, you're not allowed to innovate. Okay, we're
not innovating, this is the way it always was. So, you know,
in... to juxtapose to it, it's quite shocking. And partly I think
what it's doing is ultimately, you know, trying to subtly reinforce this
message that, you know, Esther isn't innovating, it's part of תנ"ך Tanach
and it's learning out from פסוקים psukim in תנ"ך Tanach and we're
דורש-ing doresh the פסוקים. psukim. That's the normal thing that we do.
Of course the irony is that here you have נביאים Nevi'im as
well, but, you know, somehow, and you don't דורש doresh other things
from תנ"ך. Tanach. So there's a problem. It's not enough that it's
one of the נביאים, Nevi'im, you know, it's not enough that it's
even one of the ספרי תנ"ך. sifrei Tanach. The גמרא Gemara won't
learn anything out from the other ספרי תנ"ך sifrei Tanach that's not
תורה Torah from the same principle. So by sort of raising even
this trivial thing that you can't be מחדש, mechadesh, I don't think
there's an answer to it. I think what it does is it
somehow subtly reinforces the message: everything we're doing by Esther isn't a
חידוש. chidush. Like, you know, that's all completely normal that we're דורש-ing
doresh פסוקים psukim and so on. But I think that that's, like
I said, the underlying issue that's being grappled with here as well
is where is this authority coming from?
Yes, in terms of your points, one is what's ironic is it's
the hermeneutic itself which is the juxtaposition and that's somewhat resolved by
saying, "Oh no no, it's a hermeneutic, as it were, we learned
it out." Right. So it's the דורש-ing doresh of those פסוקים psukim
which is the innovation. Right. The second thing is, I think what
the thing about the letters and their shapes is closer to what
you were saying. The implicit... the assumption here is that מצוות mitzvos
come from the
language.
Yeah, but the shape of the letters?
Anything, in other words, anything, in other words, it's
very weird to find חז״ל, Chazal, I mean that's, you know, even
in extreme of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, of the קוצו של יוד,
kutzos shel yud, but you know,
but it could be.
Maybe, but again, but again, I think that, you know, that is
I don't think that that's פשט pshat of the text. The גמרא
Gemara isn't saying like, "oh, and this would be a חידוש דבר
chiddush davar because it would affect how we would דרשן darshen something,
or this would be a חידוש דבר chiddush davar because it would
affect כתיבת ספר תורה." ktivas sefer torah. It just says like, "it's
a חידוש דבר, chiddush davar, right? You innovate, it doesn't matter, no
innovations are allowed, right?" I mean, that seems to be the sense
of the text. It's making an extreme statement that you can't innovate
even in this, this area, and then juxtaposed to all of the
reality of the
מגילה, Megillah, yes.
Question:
is this a unified view of the text or is this a
competing view? You just had all these things that were very innovative
and now you have a voice that comes and says you're not
allowed to innovate at all.
Right. You know, I don't know, I see it as... I mean,
you know, it could be... well, first of all, let's point out
this. The voice that says you can't innovate at all is the
סתם stam of the גמרא, Gemara, right? Because the original statement of
רבי ירמיה ואיתימא רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Yirmiya ve'isema Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba said they did innovate it, צופים אמרו. tzofim amru. It's
the סתם stam of the גמרא Gemara that insists you can't be
innovating. So it's hard to assume, you know, it's not like sometimes
you say we stitch together different מימרות memrot and they have different
views. Either this מימרא memra is totally happy with innovation, it's the
סתם stam that's insisting you can't, and it's the same סתם stam
that sort of, you know, the anonymous voice that was, you know,
sort of throughout the previous text. So I see it as a,
you know, as consistent or at least trying to intentionally trying to
create that, you know, contrast.
So is it like coming to praise, not to praise Caesar but
to bury? Exactly,
yes.
Exactly. So that's... I do think so that that's through the insistence
here, it's ultimately strengthening the power of the מגילה Megillah rather than
questioning it, you know. "Well, you can't be מחדש mechadesh anything," you
know, "oh, so everything we're doing by there wasn't a חידוש," chidush,
you know? That's the way I'm reading it. Okay. ואמר רבי חייא
ואיתימא רבי חייא בר אבא Ve'amar Rabbi Chiya ve'isema Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba and רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya says רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba said, תרגום של תורה אונקלוס הגר אמרו, Targum shel
Torah Onkelos HaGer amaro, and this is also interesting in terms of,
right, text and interpretation. So the אונקלוס, Onkelos, so the
תרגום Targum that we have, because they would read the תורה Torah
with the תרגום, Targum, you know, so with a standard Aramaic translation,
that was said by אונקלוס הגר. Onkelos HaGer. מפי רבי אליעזר ורבי
יהושע Mipi Rabbi Eliezer ve'Rabbi Yehoshua from the mouth of, meaning based
on the training that he received from רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, who are also the, you know, the rabbis,
the teachers of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So it's a, you know,
it's the traditional sort of rabbinic interpretation. Ultimately it's coming through the
eyes of the rabbis. Wait a minute. תרגום של נביאים יונתן בן
עוזיאל אמרו, Targum shel Nevi'im Yonasan ben Uziel amaro, the תרגום Targum
that we have on the prophets, you know, יונתן בן עוזיאל אמרו,
Yonasan ben Uziel amaro, that was written by יונתן בן עוזיאל, Yonasan
ben Uziel, who was a תלמיד talmid of הלל, Hillel, considered to
be the greatest תלמיד talmid of הלל. Hillel. The גמרא Gemara tells
a story in סוכה, Sukkah, you might remember, that when he would
learn תורה Torah and birds would fly over him they would be
consumed by fire because the heavenly angels would be surrounding him when
he was learning תורה. Torah. So that comes from יונתן בן עוזיאל.
Yonasan ben Uziel. מפי חגי זכריה ומלאכי, Mipi Chaggai Zecharya u'Malachi, which
he received from חגי זכריה ומלאכי. Chaggai Zecharya u'Malachi. Now already that's
fascinating, right? Because this is a question about is it coming from
the נביאים Nevi'im or is it coming from the rabbis, right? So
the תורה, Torah, which we've just said a minute ago is ultimately
the only entire authority of הלכה, halacha, nothing gets innovated from the
נביאים. Nevi'im. The תורה Torah is, you know, all הלכה halacha comes
from the תורה. Torah. So that interpretation, ultimate interpretation, is what is
it going to mean, you know, is through the rabbinic tradition. Whereas
נביאים, Nevi'im, okay, it's נ״ך, Nach, learns נ״ך, Nach, the נביאים, Nevi'im,
which is not about הלכה, halacha, you know, that can ultimately also
come from the, from the prophetic tradition. Because okay, it's just prophecy,
it's not about הלכה, halacha, that's ultimately interpreted through the rabbis. ונזדעזעה,
Venizdaze'a, so first of all I think that that just that statement
right there is so critical in terms of the... of exactly what
we were setting up before, you know. Nothing is innovated after the
תורה Torah and the meaning of the תורה Torah is through the
sort of rabbinic interpretation. Okay. ונזדעזעה ארץ ישראל ארבע מאות פרסה על
ארבע מאות פרסה, Venizdaze'a Eretz Yisrael arba me'os parsa al arba me'os
parsa, and when he gave over this translation, the ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael shook, ארבע מאות פרסה arba me'os parsa by ארבע מאות פרסה,
arba me'os parsa, which is presumably the size of the land of
Israel. You know, he shook the world with his translation. יצאה בת
קול ואמרה, Yatz'ah bas kol ve'amrah, a heavenly voice came out and
said, "מי הוא זה שגילה סתרי לבני אדם, Mi hu ze she'gilah
sitrai livnei adam, who is it that revealed my secrets to human
beings? You told them what the true meaning of these prophecies were."
עמד יונתן בן עוזיאל על רגליו ואמר, Amad Yonasan ben Uziel al
raglav ve'amar, "אני הוא שגליתי סתריך לבני אדם, Ani hu she'gilisi sitrecha
livnei adam, I am the one that revealed your hidden secrets to
human beings. גלוי וידוע לפניך, Galui ve'yadua lefanecha, it's be known to
you..." it's well known to you שלא לכבודי עשיתי *shelo lichvodi asiti*
ולא לכבוד בית אבא *ve-lo lichvod beit abba*, I didn't do it
for my honor or the house of my father's house, אלא לכבודך
עשיתי *ela lichvodecha asiti*. I did it for your sake שלא ירבו
מחלוקת בישראל *shelo yirbu machloket be-Yisrael* that there should not be, you
know, debates, fights in Israel. Now that's interesting like what's the מחלוקת
*machloket*? מחלוקת *machloket* about like just in the intellectual sphere, right, about
what the פסוקים Psukim *pesukim* mean. Now the idea of like ריבוי
מחלוקת *riboy machloket* is an idea that we have also, you know,
by תורה שבעל פה Torah Shebe'al Peh, *Torah she-be-al peh*. You know,
that they sort of, you know, that after the, you know, once
it was נתרבו תלמידי בית הלל ובית שמאי שלא שימשו את רבן
כל צרכם *nitrabu talmidei Beit Hillel u-Beit Shammai she-lo shimshu et rabban
kol tzorkham*, נתרבתה מחלוקת בישראל *nitrabta machloket be-Yisrael*, once there was all
these questions about the ultimate tradition and they had these different schools
and then how do you interpret it and so on. So here,
you know, it's talking about that ריבוי מחלוקת *riboy machloket* which to
us suggests like מחלוקת *machloket* suggests like Talmudic debate and halakhic debate
and it's interesting here, you know, sort of drawing on that in
this context. Interpretation resolves the מחלוקת *machloket*, it supports מחלוקת *machloket*. Only
transmission resolves מחלוקת *machloket*. Well, interpretation at least limits certain other types
of interpretation and you open the door to the possibility that there
could be an alternative voice. Once hermeneutic is authoritative, you're open to
תרבות המחלוקת *tarbut ha-machloket*. Right. I hear. Okay. ועוד ביקש לגלות תרגום
Targum של כתובים *Ve-od bikkesh le-galot Targum shel Ketuvim* and he even
wanted to reveal, you know, now by the way, notice the idea
of לגלות *le-galot*, right, because, you know, it's not again being like
innovative. He's revealing the true meaning. So he wanted to reveal the
תרגום Targum *Targum* of the כתובים *Ketuvim*. יצתה בת קול ואמרה לו
דייך *Yatzata Bat Kol ve-amra lo dayyekha*. No, enough. Not that you
can't do. מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama*? Why do you sort of have
to draw the line at the כתובים *Ketuvim*? משום דאית ביה קץ
משיח *Mishum de-it beih ketz Mashiach*, because in the פסוקים pesukim *pesukim*
you have, you know, in the כתובים *Ketuvim* you have hints to
the ultimate end of days. If you look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
he says בספר דניאל Daniyel *be-sefer Daniel*, right, that's why people love,
you know, the whole book of Daniel because of its eschatological visions
and trying to determine those, those very mysterious verses about, about תקל
תקל *tekel tekel* whatever, anyway, so you know, tried to unpack those
to figure out when ultimately משיח *Mashiach* will be. So that we
can't do. There's got to draw a line. Now I should say
about the תרגום Targum: יונתן *Targum Yonatan* that what we have in
printed in our, you know, מקראות גדולות *Mikraot Gedolot* you'll see something
called תרגום Targum יונתן בן עוזיאל *Targum Yonatan ben Uziel*. All the
scholars call that Pseudo-Jonathan, not Jonathan, because that's a תרגום Targum, *Targum*
that is on the תורה Torah, *Torah* and according to at least
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, although it doesn't say it explicitly, but it
makes it pretty much sound that Yonatan only wrote a תרגום Targum
*Targum* on נביאים Nevi'im *Nevi'im*, not on תורה Torah, *Torah*. And actually,
that is more called, you know, accurately called תרגום Targum ירושלמי *Targum
Yerushalmi*. Some actually suspect that the reason it got named תרגום Targum
יונתן *Targum Yonatan* was because it was abbreviated ת"י *tav yud* and
people thought, well, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* speaks about a תרגום Targum,
יונתן *Targum Yonatan*, it's תרגום יונתן *Targum Yonatan*, but it's actually תרגום
ירושלמי *Targum Yerushalmi*. It comes from the ארץ ישראל Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*,
most of it is in Palestinian Aramaic although there are certain strands
of Babylonian Aramaic in it, but that is considered to be relatively
late. Again, there's some debate, but generally it's assumed to be around
eighth century. What we call תרגום יונתן *Targum Yonatan* is called more
accurately תרגום ירושלמי *Targum Yerushalmi*. One of the reasons is because in
the תרגום יונתן *Targum Yonatan* quote-unquote Pseudo-Jonathan, it identifies one of ישמעאל
*Yishmael*'s wives with the name of one of Muhammad's wives. So, and
it's a name that is very late, that doesn't, it's not an
ancient Arabic name. Anyway, so we don't actually have a תרגום יונתן
*Targum Yonatan* what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is referring to. What we
have that we call תרגום יונתן *Targum Yonatan* is not what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is referring to. Yes. Back to תרגום אונקלוס Targum
Onkelos, *Targum Onkelos*, he's following רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer ורבי יהושע Yehoshua
*Rabbi Eliezer ve-Rabbi Yehoshua*, they were arguing all the time that, yeah,
what can I tell you? Okay. The תרגום של תורה Torah *Targum
shel Torah*, actually there's an interesting thing. Nachum Sarna, עליו השלום *alav
ha-shalom*, there was a time in my life when I was in
the process of getting a PhD which never actually completed, but anyway,
he was pushing me to write my dissertation on אונקלוס Onkelos *Onkelos*
and basically identify every place where אונקלוס Onkelos *Onkelos*, you know, diverges
from the פסקים *pesakim* of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, ורבי אליעזר *Rabbi
Yehoshua ve-Rabbi Eliezer*, which would be like you said, apparently it hasn't
been done. Yeah, I should. All right. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this. תרגום של תורה Torah אונקלוס הגר Onkelos HaGer, אמרו
*Targum shel Torah Onkelos ha-ger amaro*, was it really said by אונקלוס
Onkelos, *Onkelos*? והאמר רב איקא בר אבין אמר רב חננאל אמר רב
*Ve-ha-amar Rav Ika bar Avin amar Rav Chananel amar Rav*, מאי דכתיב
D'chtiv, *mai di-chtiv*, what's meant by the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* ויקראו בספר
תורת האלוקים מפורש Meforash, *Vayikrau be-sefer Torat ha-Elokim meforash*, they read, this
is in the time of Ezra right, they gather all the people
and they read from the ספר תורה Torah *Sefer Torah*, they read
from the book of God explicit ושום שכל Vesom Sechel, ויבינו במקרא
Vayavinu Bamikra, *ve-som sekhel va-yavinu ba-mikra* and they, you know, gave their
attention or you know, their intellect and they understood in the verses.
ויקראו, okay, so what does that mean? ויקראו בספר תורת האלקים, Vayikre'u
Besefer Torat Ha-Elokim, זה מקרא, Zeh Mikra, they read the verses. מפורש,
explicit, זה תרגום, Zeh Targum, which explicates, which is מפרש, Mefareish, which
translates. ושום שכל, אלו הפסוקים, Elu Hapsukim, so in order to truly
understand it, this is the division of the verses. Where does one
verse end and the next verse begin? ויבינו במקרא, and they truly
understood the verses, אלו פסקי טעמים, Elu Piskei Te'amim, that's also like,
you know, the טראפ Trup as we would say, which also gives
you the, you know, the the the punctuation in the middle of
the verse. Okay, so אמרי לה Amrei Lei and some say אלו
המסורה, Elu Hamesora, this is the מסורה Mesora which is, you know,
the exact sort of accounting of the letters and, you know, and
and like which words are מלא Malei and חסר Chaser and so
on. So again you see that all of that was number one,
similar to some of the statements before, like at least, you know,
attributed way back, and certainly the תרגום is attributed way back. So
how could you say אונקלוס Onkelos said it? So once more we
have the answer: שכחום וחזרו ויסדום. Shachechum Vechazru Veyasdum. Fine, אונקלוס didn't
innovate it; it was forgotten and he re-established it. So now we
have that the interpretation of the תורה, Torah. right, and this sort
of goes back to many other דמי חז"ל Dmei Chazal that you
might be know, you know, anything כל מה שעתיד תלמיד ותיק להתחדש
כבר נאמר למשה מסיני. Kol mah she'atid talmid vatik lehitchadesh kvar ne'emar
leMoshe miSinai. You know, whatever eventually is going to be said by
any תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham was already said at הר סיני. Har
Sinai. So on one hand, you know, תורה Torah שבעל פה, the
whole process of interpretation and innovation, and at the other hand, it's
always being said that it's all ultimately going back to what was
said at הר סיני Har Sinai and therefore it's not really innovating
anything. So here you have, right, as the same idea, the Rabbis,
you know, אונקלוס הגר, תלמיד Talmid of רבי Rebbi, אליעזר and רבי
Rebbi יהושע, Yehoshua gives the authoritative interpretation of the תורה, Torah, so
it's the תורה Torah through the Rabbinic lens, its binding, its significant
meaning, as opposed, you know, again as opposed to תנ"ך, Tanach, נ"ך,
Nach, which could be through the prophetic sort of tradition, because in
the end it's just נ"ך. Nach. Okay, but this is sort of
the binding meaning is through the Rabbinic tradition and this is ultimately,
even though it's that way, ultimately it's just getting us back to
what it always meant. It's not really innovating anything. Okay, so part
of what sort of, you know, gives strength to the whole Rabbinic
tradition is the assertion that ultimately it's just getting us back to
what always was the case and what it always meant. An interesting
side point by the פסוק ויקראו בספר תורת האלקים, Pasuk Vayikre'u Besefer
Torat Ha-Elokim, if you look at רש"י Rashi near the גליון הש"ס,
Gilyon HaShas, רש"י says בספר עזרא כתיב, Besefer Ezra ktiv, but if
you look at the תורה אור, Torah Or, you see it's a
פסוק pasuk in נחמיה. Nechemiah. And the answer is, anybody know the
answer? It's that עזרא נחמיה Ezra Nechemiah was one book. It was
the Christians that divided it into two books, but in the sort
of, you know, in the Rabbinic tradition, it was all the book
of עזרא. Ezra. Okay, so let's do a little bit more here
in the גמרא. Gemara Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
מאי שנא דאורייתא דלא אזדעזעה ועד נביאים אזדעזעה? Mai shna d'Oraita d'lo
izdazeia ve'ad Nevi'im izdazeia? Why did the world not tremble when it
interpreted the biblical verses, when the translation was given, but it trembled
when the translation was given on the prophetic books? By the way,
the later, you know, we'll be dealing later in the מסכת Masechet
with the whole idea of the translation of the תורה Torah into
Greek. Okay, so it's worth keeping this in mind. So the גמרא
Gemara says דאורייתא מפרשן מילי. Oraita mefarsham milsa. No, you know, the
פסוקים pesukim, in the תורה Torah, are more explicit, so it's not
completely revealing something that was that was, you know, that was cryptic
beforehand. נביאים איכא מילי דמפרשן ואיכא מילי דמסתתמן, Nevi'im ika mili d'mifarshei
v'ika mili d'mistammei, in the in the prophets, some things are quite
clear, some things are quite sealed or quite unclear, cryptic, and therefore
it was a true like, you know, revealing of the secret, things
that were very unclear beforehand. דכתיב, and I'll give you an example:
ביום ההוא יגדל המספד בירושלים כמספד הדדרימון בבקעת מגידון. Bayom hahu yigdal
hamisped biYerushalayim k'misped Hadadrimmon bevikat Megiddo. On that day the, you know,
the wailing will will increase in Jerusalem, you know, like the like
the eulogy or like the wailing at the time of הדדרימון Hadadrimmon
in the valley of מגידו. Megiddo. Now that's a problem, because there
was never a מספד, Misped, eulogy, for הדדרימון Hadadrimmon in the valley
of מגידו. Megiddo. ואמר רב יוסף, Ve'amar Rav Yosef, and said רב
יוסף, Rav Yosef, or not that we know of from other verses,
אלמלא תרגומא דהאי קרא לא ידעינא מאי קאמר, Ilmalei Targuma d'hai kra
lo yadina mai ka'amar, if it wasn't for the תרגום of this
verse, I wouldn't know what it means. But here's the תרגום: ביומא
ההוא יסגי מספדא בירושלם, Bayom hahu yisgei mispeda biYerushalayim,
on that day the eulogizing, the wailing, will increase in Jerusalem, כמספדא
דאחאב בר עמרי דקטל יתיה הדדרימון בן טברימון ברמות גלעד וכמספדא דיאשיהו
בר אמון דקטל יתיה פרעה חגירא בבקעת מגידו, k'mispeda d'Achav bar Omri
d'kataleih yateih Hadadrimmon ben Tabrimmon beRamot Gilead v'chamispeda d'Yoshiyahu bar Amon d'kataleih
yateih Par'oh chagira bevikat Megiddo, like the wailing, like the מספד, Misped,
the
wailing of אחאב בר עמרי Achav bar Omri who was slaughtered by,
who was killed by הדדרימון בן טברימון, Hadadrimmon ben Tabrimmon, רמות גלעד,
Ramot Gilead, now that wasn't in בבקעת מגידו, bevikat Megiddo, that was
in רמות גלעד, Ramot Gilead, and the מספד Misped of יאשיהו בר
אמון Yoshiyahu bar Amon that פרעה חגירא Par'oh chagira killed him בבקעת
מגידו, bevikat Megiddo, in the valley of מגידו. Megiddo. So the תרגום
makes it clear to us that this is talking about two eulogies,
not one, and therefore הדדרימון Hadadrimmon never happened in בבקעת מגידו. bevikat
Megiddo. it's like and in בבקעת מגדו. be-bik'at Megiddo. Now again to
sort of give us an example of a cryptic, prophetic verse that's
interpreted by the תרגום, this is one that was a little bit
of a problem, you know, and it's not something that would have
been outside of our ability to maybe have even sort of come
up with ourselves, you know, there's plenty of these prophecies that you
don't know what the heck they're talking about. So I don't know,
I really can't explain why the גמרא Gemara gives this as an
example of to to to sort of illustrate how much more, you
know, innovative or not innovative, right, but how much more revealing the
תרגום of the נביאים Nevi'im was over the תרגום of the תורה.
Torah You know, again, unless the point is the opposite, sort of
what we were saying before. If this is considered to be a
revealing of something that was cryptic, then anything that's done in terms
of interpreting the תורה Torah, is implicitly more obvious than this. So
therefore, any rabbinic interpretation of the תורה, Torah. any תרגום of the
תורה Torah is not really, you know, it's less of a חידוש
chiddush than just interpreting which again reinforces the strength of the rabbinic
interpretation, right? For example, if you look at אונקלוס, our תרגום אונקלוס,
Targum Onkelos is it exactly the תרגום אונקלוס Targum Onkelos the גמרא
Gemara had is some debate, but you know, you look at our
תרגום אונקלוס Targum Onkelos on לא תבשל גדי בחלב אמו, lo tevashel
gedi ba-halev immo, תרגום אונקלוס translates it as literally in the תרגום,
he has it לא תאכלון בשר בחלב. lo tokhelun besar ba-halav. So
don't eat בשר בחלב. besar ba-halav. That's the translation. You know אונקלוס
is pretty literal. Okay, but that's the translation of לא תבשל גדי
בחלב אמו. lo tevashel gedi ba-halev immo. So again, the only thing
I can understand here is that by giving this as showing you
how revelatory the the interpretation of נביאים Nevi'im is, it's underscored how
פשט peshat the interpretation of the תורה Torah is, you know, and
again that's like the rabbinic interpretation. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. ראיתי אני, Ra'iti ani, so so this is going
to give us another statement of רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah that seems
like off topic though it's somewhat connected. But anyway, it's another statement
of רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah ואיבעית אימא רב חייא בר אבא. ve-iba'it
eima Rav Hiyya bar Abba. וראיתי אני דניאל לבדי את המראה, ve-ra'iti
ani Daniyel levaddi et ha-mareh, I דניאל Daniyel myself saw the vision.
והאנשים אשר היו עמי לא ראו ve-ha-anashim asher hayu immi lo ra'u
את המראה, et ha-mareh, the vision. אבל חרדה גדולה נפלה עליהם, aval
haradah gedolah naflah aleihem, but a great trembling fell upon them. ויברחו
בהחבא, va-yivrehu be-hahbe, and they ran away in in hiding. So מאן
נינהו אנשים, man ninhu anashim, who were these people that were with
דניאל Daniyel that did not see the vision that דניאל Daniyel saw?
אמר רב ירמיה ואיבעית אימא רב חייא בר אבא, Amar Rav Yirmiyah
ve-iba'it eima Rav Hiyya bar Abba, זה חגי זכריה ומלאכי. zeh Hagai
Zekharyah u-Malakhi. This is חגי זכריה ומלאכי, Hagai Zekharyah u-Malakhi, some of
the great נביאים nevi'im at that time. So the גמרא Gemara says
אינהו עדיפי מיניה ואיהו עדיף מינהו. inhu adifei minei ve-ihu adif minhu.
They were greater than him in some ways, but he was greater
than them. אינהו עדיפי מיניה, inhu adifei minei, they were greater than
he, דאינהו נביאי ואיהו לא נביא. de-inhu nevi'ei ve-ihu lo navi. They
were נביאים nevi'im and he was not a נביא. navi. Now, דניאל
Daniyel had all these visions, what do you exactly mean he wasn't
a נביא? navi? So רש״י Rashi says דאינהו נביאי, de-inhu nevi'ei, רש״י
Rashi says here I don't know, like 20 lines down the narrow
lines, שנתנבאו לישראל בשליחותו של מקום shenitnab'u le-Yisrael bi-shlihuto shel Makom והוא
לא נשתלח לישראל בשום נבואה. ve-hu lo nishtalah le-Yisrael be-shum nevu'ah. And
that is a very important in terms of the rabbinic idea of
what the whole point of prophecy is. Prophecy isn't just for your
own personal ability to have a vision of God. Prophecy is אהרן
אחיך יהיה נביאך, Aharon ahikha yihyeh nevi'ekha, right, will be your נביאך,
nevi'ekha, will be your communicator. A נביא navi is so ניב שפתים
niv sefatayim is the speech of the lips. Right, a נביא navi
is one who brings God's message to the people, not one who
has a divine vision. Okay, so they were נביאים nevi'im and he
was not a נביא. navi. So in one way, you know, their
status right is I mean דניאל Daniyel is a ספר תנ״ך, sefer
Tanakh, but nobody calls דניאל a נביא. navi. Okay, so they were
נביאים nevi'im, and he is not a נביא. navi. So they are
greater than he, but ואיהו עדיף מינהו, ve-ihu adif minhu, but he
was greater than them, דאיהו חזא ואינהו לא חזו. de-ihu haza ve-inhu
lo hazu. He was maybe able to have visions that they couldn't
have. Exactly this difference. He had certain type of, you know, mystical
visions that they did not have, but that wasn't their role. Their
role was to be נביאים, Nevi'im was to bring God's message to
the people. Okay, וכי מאחר דלא חזו, ve-khei me-ahar de-lo hazu, if
they didn't if they didn't see, מאי טעמא איבעיתו, mai ta'ama iv'itu,
so how come they got scared? So אף על גב דאינהו לא
חזו, af al gav de-inhu lo hazu, even though they didn't see,
מזלייהו חזו. mazleyhu hazu. Their מזל mazel saw, you know, sometimes you
sense something is even if you can't really see. Sort of like
בלעם's Bil'am donkey that knew the angel was there. אמר רבינא, Amar
Ravina, שמע מינה, shema mina, we see from this, האי מאן דמיבעית,
hai man de-miv'it, if all of a sudden you get you you
know, you start trembling and you get you get this, you know,
fear that comes over you, you just feel afraid and you don't
know what it's about, אף על גב דאיהו לא חזי, af al
gav de-ihu lo hazi, even though you're not seeing something, מזליה חזי,
mazleh hazi, your מזל mazel is see is sensing something. There's some
spiritual force out there that might do you damage. So there's probably
some type of a שד shed or something of that nature. So
מאי תקנתיה, mai takanteih, what do you do? ליקרי קריאת שמע, likrei
Kri'at Shema, say קריאת שמע, Kri'at Shema, that'll protect you. ואי קאי
במקום הטינופת, ve-i ka'ei be-makom ha-tinofet, and if you're in a place
of filth, like you're in a, you know, bathroom or in a
at an alleyway that's got excrement or whatever and you can't say
קריאת שמע, Kri'at Shema, לינשוף מדוכתיה ארבע גרמידי, linshof midukteih arba garmidei,
jump from your place four אמות, ammot, ואי לא, ve-i lo, and
then and then you'll be out of the וקאים במקום הטינופת, v'ka'im
b'mokom hachinofesh, and if you're in a place of filth like you're
in a bathroom or an alleyway that's got excrement or whatever, and
you can't say קריאת שמע, Krias Shema, לינשוף מדוכתיה ארבע גרמידי, linshof
miduchtei arba gamidei, jump from your place four אמות, amos, ואי, v'ie,
and then you'll be out of the, you maybe walked into the
hiding place of this שד sheid or something. So you jump four
אמות amos out and then maybe by jumping, you know, he won't
follow you, you'll get out of that zone. ואי לא, v'im lo,
and if not, you can't do that, לימא הכי, leima hachi, say
this. עיזא דבי טבחי שמינא מינאי, iza d'bei tapachei shmeina minai, the
goats of the slaughterhouse are fatter than me. So what do you
want with me, go get some of the goats of the slaughterhouse?
I don't know what to do with that. Anyway, okay. So, so
now we, so anyway, but again, a lot of these things, again,
about the weight and the power of the נביאים Nevi'im in contrast
to the תורה, Torah but again, the תורה Torah. through the rabbinic
lens, and I think in a way, you know, really somehow by
making these extreme statements about it's not innovative, and we're not innovating,
and נביאים don't innovate, it in general reinforces general rabbinic interpretation of
the תורה, Torah, but also the fact that מגילה Megillah is therefore
not really an innovation and it's all completely treated the same way
as we would the פסוקים pesukim in the תורה. Torah Okay, let's,
I know I have to leave a little early, but let's at
least turn the page. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
see I come back and all of a sudden we're behind again.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: והא דאמרת מדינה ומדינה ועיר
ועיר לדרשה, v'ha she'amarta midinah u'midinah v'ir v'ir lidrashah, now that we're
דורשנינג darshening those פסוקים, right, to tell you, you know, cities nearby
and other types of הלכות, halachos, so משפחה ומשפחה, mishpachah u'mishpachah, I
mean villages near cities, למאי אתא, l'mai ata, what's משפחה ומשפחה mishpachah
u'mishpachah coming to tell you? אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא להביא משפחות
כהונה ולויה שמבטלין עבודתן ובאים לשמוע מקרא מגילה, Amar Rabbi Yose bar
Chanina l'havi mishpachot kehunah u'leviyah she'mvatlin avodatan u'ba'im lishmo'a mikra megillah, to
tell you all families have to do it, even the families of
כהנים Kohanim and לוים, Levi'im, they leave the עבודה avodah in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and they come to listen to the מגילה.
Megillah. So now, you know, on the one hand, we again following
the idea that we've been treating the מגילה, Megillah, you know, as
biblical verses and interpreting them to understand, you know, the nature of
the מצוה, mitzvah, here we're treating the מצוה mitzvah of מגילה Megillah
as greater weight than doing the עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. Okay, so similar, we're just giving it so much weight.
And I mean תוספות Tosafot even asks, why do you have to
be מבטל mevatel anything? Go listen to מגילה Megillah and then go
do your עבודה, avodah, what's the big problem? So, you know, the
fact is that it's not really such a relevant הלכה. halachah. I
mean, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, the end of the first
like four lines down in the I mean the end of the
last wide line in תוספות, Tosafot, four lines from the top of
the page. It says, ואם תאמר ויעשו עבודתן מיד ואחר כך יקראו
את המגילה לבדם. v'im tomar v'ya'asu avodatan miyad v'achar kach yikre'u et
hamigillah l'vadam. You know, go ahead, do the עבודה, avodah, bring the
תמיד, tamid, so you maybe missed the reading first thing in the
morning, but you bring the תמיד tamid and then you have your
own little private מנין. minyan. ויש לומר דטוב לקרותו עם הצבור משום
דהוי טפי פרסומי ניסא. v'yesh lomar detov l'ikre'o im hatzibbur mishum d'havi
tfei pirsumei nisa. Aye, but you want to do with everybody else
because it's a bigger פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, you want to get
the שחרית, shacharis, so therefore you have to postpone the תמיד tamid
in order to get the מגילה Megillah in the morning. Now, again,
when this is normally read, it's interpreted, you know, about the weight
of this idea of פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, which is how the
גמרא's Gemara going to sort of as the theme the גמרא's Gemara
going to bring in later. But at this stage, it hasn't introduced
the idea of פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, it's really not clear at
all when you would really have this type of a conflict. And
again, I think that it's, you know, really the first point is
reinforcing this issue about giving this tremendous weight to the מצוה mitzvah
of מגילה. Megillah. We've already given weight to the verses of the
מגילה Megillah and their sort of, you know, and their weight, and
treating them like biblical verses and now we're giving weight to the
מצוה mitzvah of מגילה. Megillah. Yes. And it's an interesting. Right. Right.
Right. And the עבודה avodah being. Interesting, interesting. So that that's a
very good point, that a holiday of גלות Galut without עבודה avodah
outweighs an ex-post-facto kind of of תורה Torah and the rabbinic enterprise
sort of, you know, come you know, replacing the centrality of the
קרבנות. korbanot. Very interesting. Right right right. No no no, we're actually
that's going to continue in a minute because the גמרא Gemara is
then going to deal with תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah versus קרבנות. korbanot.
So it's a very good point. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: okay. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב כהנים בעבודתם לוים בדוכנם
ישראל במעמדם, d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Kohanim be'avodatam Levi'im b'duchanam Yisrael
b'ma'amadam, the כהנים Kohanim doing the עבודה, avodah, לוים Levi'im on the
דוכן duchan and doing the שירה, shirah, and the ישראל in the
מעמד, ma'amad, which we just learned what that was in מגילה, Megillah,
standing by the קרבנות korbanot or in the various cities, כולם מבטלין
עבודתן ובאים לשמוע מקרא מגילה, kulam mevatlin avodatan u'ba'im lishmo'a mikra megillah,
they all leave their עבודה avodah and come to hear the מגילה.
Megillah. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, כהנים בעבודתם
לוים בדוכנם ישראל במעמדם כולם מבטלין עבודתן ובאים לשמוע מקרא מגילה. Kohanim
be'avodatam Levi'im b'duchanam Yisrael b'ma'amadam kulam mevatlin avodatan u'ba'im lishmo'a mikra megillah.
I very much like the point that David made because you could
also imagine that once there is a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash in
the time of the second בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you know, that
פורים Purim would be very downplayed, you know, some גלות Galut holiday
whatever, it was because they were in in trouble because they were
in גלות, Galut, like it's no longer relevant to us. So it's
very it's an excellent point. מכאן סמכו של בית רבי, mikan samchos
shel beit rebbi, this is the support of the house of רבי,
Rebbi שמבטלין תלמוד תורה ובאים לשמוע מקרא מגילה. she'mevatlin talmud torah u'ba'im
lishmo'a mikra megillah. In his time, there was no longer בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. What's the base for בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash but תלמוד
תורה, Talmud Torah, and he said that you would stop your תורה
Torah study, like you know, in order to come and hear the
מגילה. Megillah. קל וחומר מעבודה, kal v'chomer me'avodah, and it's a קל
וחומר kal v'chomer from עבודה. avodah. And now this is interesting because
this is the question of which is... higher in the hierarchy. ומה
עבודה שהיא חמורה מבטלין, U'ma avodah she-hi chamura mevatlin, if you stop
the עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash for מגילה, Megilla,
תלמוד תורה לא כל שכן? Talmud Torah lo kol she-kein? How much
more so would you stop תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, which is fascinating
because it's putting תורה Torah at a lower level than the עבודה.
avodah. The גמרא Gemara is not going to let that stay there.
What, is עבודה avodah really weightier than תלמוד תורה? Talmud Torah? הא
כתיב, Ha ksiv, the verse says: ויהי בהיות יהושע ביריחו, Vayehi bihyos
Yehoshua b'Yericho, when יהושע Yehoshua was in Jericho, וישא עיניו וירא והנה
איש עמד לנגדו, vanyisa einav vayar vehineh ish omeid l'negdo, there's a
person standing opposite him, and right, וישתחו vayishtachu and he bowed down,
and he said, you know, הלנו אתה אם לצרינו, halanu ata im
l'tzareinu, are you for us or are you one of our enemies?
And he said, שר צבא השם עתה באתי, Sar tzeva Hashem ata
basi, no, I'm an angel of God. So the גמרא Gemara first
says, היכי עביד הכי? Heichi avid hachi? How did he bow down
on the ground? ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי אסור לאדם שיתן שלום
לחבירו בלילה—oh v'amar Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi asur l'adam sheyiten shalom lachaveiro
balaylah no, it's not asking bowing down—ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי אסור
לאדם שיתן שלום לחבירו בלילה, v'amar Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi asur l'adam
sheyiten shalom lachaveiro balaylah, חוששין שמא שד הוא, chosheshin shema sheid hu,
going back to the whole שד sheid problem. You can't greet somebody
at night. תוספות Tosafot says we don't mean in a city, we
mean out in the fields, you know, because we should be afraid
that you can't see the person and maybe they're just a שד
sheid dressing up as a human. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
שאני התם דאמר ליה כי אני שר צבא השם, shani hatam d'amar
lei ki ani sar tzeva Hashem, no, because he identified himself as
an angel of God. But the גמרא Gemara, says, ודילמא משקרי, v'dilma
meshakrei, maybe he was lying? גמירי דלא מפקי שם שמים לבטלה. Gmiri
d'lo mafki shem shamayim l'vatala. No, we know שדים sheidim won't say
God's name לבטלה, l'vatala, so it's obviously he wouldn't have been lying.
Although he said that after יהושע Yehoshua greeted him, didn't he? Anyways,
alright. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei, that's not relevant to our point.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so the angel said to him—and there's a
whole discussion in תוספות Tosafot how the גמרא sort of, you know,
is able to bring in, you know, insert this story, where it
gets the hints from the verses. But we won't worry about that.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, the angel said to him: אמש ביטלתם תמיד
של בין הערבים. Emesh bitaltem tamid shel bein ha-arbayim. Last night, now
it's nighttime, right before nightfall, you were too busy with your setting
up, you know, your, you know, the siege, that you didn't bring
the afternoon תמיד. tamid. ועכשיו, V'achshav, and now it's night, and now
you could—what are you doing? There's no war, you're not fighting war
at night, so you could be learning תורה. ביטלתם תלמוד תורה. Bitaltem
Talmud Torah. You're not doing תורה, you know, you're letting the war,
you know, override all these other things. So you're not learning תורה
right now. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so יהושע Yehoshua, said to him:
על איזה מהן באת? Al eizeh mehen basa? Which one motivated you
to come? Which one was more serious? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he
said to him: עתה באתי. Ata basi. Now I've come. It was
the ביטול תלמוד תורה, bitul Talmud Torah, that's what caused me to
come and give you this מוסר. mussar. מיד, Miyad, immediately: וילן יהושע
בלילה ההוא בתוך העמק. Vayalen Yehoshua balaylah hahu besoch ha-emek. יהושע slept
at night in the valley. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabi Yochanan, says
רבי יוחנן: Rabi Yochanan: מלמד שלן בעומקה של הלכה. melamed she-lan b'omka
shel halacha. So he slept in the depths of הלכה, halacha, meaning
that he, you know, started really learning הלכה. halacha. Notice how תורה
is identified as הלכה. halacha. So he, he got the message. Now
by the way, there's a problem that that פסוק is not said
by יריחו, Yericho, it's said by העי. Ai. So anyway, there's a
very interesting תוספות, Tosafot, if you look at the bottom of ג
עמוד א, gimel amud aleph, תוספות Tosafot says: וילן יהושע בלילה ההוא
בתוך העמק, Vayalen Yehoshua balaylah hahu besoch ha-emek, לא כתיב בהאי קרא
כן אלא כשצר יריחו כתיב וילן בלילה ההוא בתוך העם, lo ksiv
b'hai kra kein ela k'she-tzar Yericho ksiv vayalen balaylah hahu besoch ha-am,
וכשצר על העי כתיב וילך יהושע בלילה ההוא בתוך העמק. u'keshetzar al
ha-Ai ksiv vayelech Yehoshua balaylah hahu besoch ha-emek. So one has עמק
emek and one has וילן. vayalen. ודרך הש"ס לקצר פסוקים ולערבם יחד,
V'derech ha-Shas l'katzeir pesukim u'l'arvam yachad, כמו בנותן קצת בכמה לו. k'mo
b'nosein ktzas b'chama lo. Sometimes the גמרא just, you know, splits verses
and combines verses and it's not being, it's not a direct quote.
It's quoting two פסוקים together, splices, right. Anyway, so you see that
תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah was more important than קרבנות. korbanot. ואמר רב
שמואל בר אוניא גדול תלמוד תורה יותר מהקרבת תמידין. V'amar Rav Shmuel
bar Unya gadol Talmud Torah yoseir me-hakravat t'midin. And from this we
learn a principle, that תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is weightier even than
the daily sacrifices. שנאמר עתה באתי. Shene-emar ata basi. Now I've come.
So oh, you see? So the גמרא says, how could רבי make
a קל וחומר kal v'chomer that you're מבטל תלמוד תורה? mevatel Talmud
Torah? לא קשיא הא דרבים הא דיחיד. Lo kashya ha d'rabim ha
d'yachid. It's a difference whether it is תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah of
רבים rabim or תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah of the יחיד. yachid. תלמוד
תורה Talmud Torah of the רבים rabim like יהושע, that's weightier than
קרבנות. korbanot. תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah of an individual, that's less weighty.
So which raises the question when, when רבי says you're מבטל תלמוד
תורה mevatel Talmud Torah for מקרא מגילה, mikra Megilla, are you even
מבטל תלמוד תורה דרבים? mevatel Talmud Torah d'rabim? Right, 'cause now we,
now we haven't said yes or no, but we said תלמוד תורה
דרבים Talmud Torah d'rabim is weightier than קרבנות. korbanot. The קל וחומר
kal v'chomer really only applies by תלמוד תורה דיחיד. Talmud Torah d'yachid.
Read one more thing I can't stop myself. So the גמרא says,
ותלמוד תורה דיחיד קל? V'Talmud Torah d'yachid kal? Is the תלמוד תורה
Talmud Torah of an individual less weighty? Doesn't even want to concede
that point. והתנן נשים במועד מענות אבל לא מטפחות. V'hatnan nashim b'moed
meanos aval lo metapchot. If you have a funeral on חול המועד,
chol ha-moed, the women who would be the wailers could be מענות
meanos but they could not like beat on the breast. The מענות
meanos would be like saying, you know, eulogizing or, you know, wailing
and having everybody wail with them, but they couldn't do the beating
on the breast. ורבי ישמעאל אומר אם היו סמוכות למיטה מטפחות. V'Rabi
Yishmael omeir im hayu s'muchos lamitah metapchos. If they were right near
the, the coffin, מטפחות, metapchos, they could even do the, the, you
know, the beating or a clapping, whatever they would do. בראשי חדשים
ובחנוכה ובפורים מענות ומטפחות בזה ובזה. B'roshei chodashim u'v'Chanukah u'v'Purim meanos u'metapchos
bezeh u'vezeh. Rosh Chodesh, Chanukah, and Purim, which are less weighty than
חול המועד, chol ha-moed, מענות ומטפחות בזה ובזה. meanos u'metapchos bezeh u'vezeh.
They can do both the מענות meanos and the מטפחות, metapchos, the
wailing and the beating on the breast, אבל לא מקוננות, aval lo
m'konenot, they can't do the... The קינה, kinah, the what's the word
for קינה? kinah? The lamentations, dirges, which apparently was they would say
something and then everybody would respond back and that would be seen
as even a bigger public type of an event or greater way,
greater mourning. ואמר רבא בר הונא אין מועד בפני תלמיד חכם. V'amar
Rava bar Huna ein mo'ed bifnei talmid chacham. But by the death
of a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, חול המועד Chol HaMoed isn't relevant.
You do the full eulogizing and wailing. כל שכן חנוכה ופורים. kol
shekein Chanukah u'Purim. How much more so חנוכה Chanukah and פורים! Purim!
So you see that the death of a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
would override those concerns. So you see the one individual תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham and the weight of חנוכה Chanukah and פורים Purim gives
way to even one תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. So this isn't that
the תלמוד תורה ביחיד Talmud Torah b'yachid is weightier than the עבודה,
avodah, but the תלמוד תורה ביחיד Talmud Torah b'yachid should be at
least weightier than מקרא מגילה mikra megillah because here the eulogizing of
an individual תלמיד חכם talmid chacham is weightier than חנוכה. Chanukah. Says
the גמרא, כבוד תורה חמור, kvod torah chamur, wait, that's honoring the
Torah, not the act of learning the Torah. That's showing the honor
that's due to the Torah. כבוד תורה דיחיד חמור. kvod torah d'yachid
chamur. Yes, giving honor to the Torah, that is weightier and that
would override the aspects of חנוכה Chanukah and פורים Purim and that
would override if you had to go to a funeral, you had
to show כבוד kavod to a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham who died,
that would take precedence over מקרא מגילה, mikra megillah, that's true. תלמוד
תורה דיחיד קל. talmud torah d'yachid kal. But the act of learning
Torah, that can give way to the act of reading the מגילה.
Megillah. So now we have learned that the עבודה avodah gives way
to the מגילה, Megillah, where there would be a conflict, it's hard
to understand, but תורה gives way, you don't say "yeah, it's such
a big, אך, och, so much שטיקל shtikel תורה goes on there
when you try to go to the שול shul on פורים Purim
there's all this whatever, I'm just gonna stay at home, I'm just
gonna learn." No. תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah gives way to מקרא מגילה,
mikra megillah, okay. The one thing that we haven't sort of made
clear is, is תלמוד תורה דרבים Talmud Torah d'rabbim give way? Because
that we said is even higher on the hierarchy. Okay, to be
continued.